Alberto Lumbreras | CV

□ +33 634 266 794 • ☑ alberto.lumbreras@irit.fr
② www.albertolumbreras.net • in albertolumbreras • ☑ albertlumbreras
☑ alumbreras

Resources Humaines 5 octobre 2016 CNRS

Chère Madame, Cher Monsieur,

Veuillez trouver ci-joint mon CV avec des copies et des attestations de mes contrats.

Après mon diplome d'Ingenieur des Télécomunications (2005) Ingénieur de Recherche à Telefónica Investigación y Desarrollo (R&D)(2004–2010) : 2 ans en CDD et 4 ans en CDI.

— CDD 3 mois du 2/11/2004 au 28/02/2005

Pièces fournies :

- PIECE 1A : Copie du contrat
- PIECE 1B : Copie basique du Ministère de l'Emploi
- Prolongation CDD 3 mois du 29/02/2005 au 28/05/2005
- CDD 6 mois du 29/05/2005 au 28/11/2005

Pièces fournies :

- PIECE 2A : Copie du contrat
- PIECE 2B : Copie basique du Ministère de l'Emploi
- Prolongation CDD du 29/11/2005 au 28/10/2006

Pièces fournies :

- PIECE 3A: Copie du contrat de prologantion
- PIECE 3B : Copie basique du Ministère de l'Emploi
- Transformation du CDD à CDI
 - PIECE 4 : Copie basique du Ministère de l'Emploi

Pendant mon master 2010-2012 :

Ingénieur de Recherche à l'Université Politéchnique de la Catalogne (2010–2012)

- CDD 6 mois à temps partiel du 28/07/2010 au 27/01/2011 Pièce fournie :
 - PIECE 5 : Copie basique du Ministère de l'Emploi
- Prolongation CDD 6 mois du 28/01/2011 au 27/06/2010
- CDD journée à plein temps du 16/05/2011 au 31/12/2011
 - Pièce fournie :
 - PIECE 6 : Copie basique du Ministère de l'Emploi.
- Project Harvest (http://www.pascal-network.org/?q=node/19) de 3 mois.

Pièce fournie :

• PIECE 7 : Copie "Request for reimbursement of costs".

Pendant ma thèse CIFRE 2013–2016 : Ingénieur de Recherche à Technicolor R&I (2013–2016).

— CDD 3 ans

Pièce fournie :

• PIECE 8 : Copie du contrat

Je reste à votre entière disposition pour tout complément d'information ou pièce que vous pourriez souhaiter.

Veuillez agréer, Madame, Monsieur, l'expression de mes respectueuses salutations,

Alberto Lumbreras

Alberto Lumbreras | CV

 \square +33 634 266 794 • \square alberto.lumbreras@irit.fr

♦ www.albertolumbreras.net• in albertolumbreras• Jalumbreras

Personal information

Date and place of birth: April 4th 1981, Barcelona

Nationality: Spanish

Education

Education	
PhD, Computer Science	Feb 2013-2016
Université de Lyon 2	Lyon
Industrial PhD (CIFRE) in Technicolor R&D (Rennes).	
Supervisors:	
Bertrand Jouve (CNRS, U. Toulouse 2. Previously : U. Lyon 2),	
Julien Velcin (Université Lyon 2, ERIC Lab),	
Marie Guégan (Technicolor)	
Master, Artificial Intelligence	2009–2012
Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya	Barcelona
(2-year programme. Score : 7,69/10)	
BSc, Telecommunication Engineering	1999–2005
Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya	Barcelona
(5-year programme)	
Summer Schools.	
Network analysis and applications	August 2014
http://www.quantware.ups-tlse.fr/ecoleluchon2014/	Luchon
Machine Learning Summer School	May 2014

http://www. quantware. ups-tlse. fr/ecoleluchon2014/LuchonMachine Learning Summer SchoolMay 2014http://mlss2014. hiit. fi/ReykjavikStructure and dynamics of complex networksApril 2014http://leshouches2014. weebly. com/Les HouchesLisbon Machine Learning SchoolJuly 2011http://lxmls.it.pt/2011/Home.htmlLisbon

Research experience (2004-2012)

Research Engineer 2004–2010

Telefónica Investigación y Desarrollo (Telefónica Research)

Barcelona

I worked for 6 years in the research branch of Telefónica (multinational broadband and telecommunications provider) as a Research Engineer. As such, I have been involved in European research projects (founded by the FP7 program) as well as in internal research projects, mainly for the Internet and the Mobile divisions of the company. My tasks ranged from the design and implementation of algorithms to the writing of project proposals and coordination of small research teams in exploratory areas. Some of these projects are:

- **Expert Systems (2004–2006)**: design and implementation of an expert system that monitors and automatically corrects failures in a tier center of a Europan grid computing network for scientific research, coordinated by the CERN (Conseil Européen pour la Recherche Nucléaire)
- Peer-to-Peer Networks (2006–2007): design and implementation of P2P (bluetooth and IPTV) content distribution, prototypes development and technical analysis of feasibility for its integration in the Telefónica platform.
- Movisphere (corporate spin-off) (2008-2009): as a part of a two-people team, I moved to Vancouver for three months to create a spin-off founded by Telefónica in collaboration with the Center for Digital Media. Movisphere was a multi-platform (mobile, TV, PC) service of casual games. The project received the following awards:
 - Best New Business Opportunity at Telefónica's Second Annual Research Fair. http://thecdm.ca/projects/archives/movisphere
 - Honoree in the Integrated Mobile Project category at the 13th Webby Awards. http://tinyurl.com/webbyawards-movisphere
- Recommender Systems & User Profiling (2009–2010): I worked in a platform to integrate all recommendations and user profiling services in Telefónica.

Research Engineer 2010–2012

Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya

Barcelona

Laboratory for Relational Algorithmics, Complexity and Learning.

I developed and implemented algorithms and system prototypes for data mining, sentiment analysis and recommender systems. I also helped in the organization of workshops and conferences hosted by our research lab. I was also involved in technology transfer projects to help industrial partners in adapting the algorithms developed in the lab. The following are two of the main projects:

- **Sentiment Analysis and Stream Mining**: I adapted the popular MOA software (stream data mining) to be used with particular sentiment analysis methods in social networks streams. I worked together with the researchers at the University of Waikato (New Zealand) who created MOA.
- Recommender Systems: I designed and implemented a prototype of a content recommender system for social networks.

Research Engineer – Thèse CIFRE

2013-2016

Technicolor R&I

Rennes

In the context of a CIFRE thesis (industrial thesis) I worked as a Research Engineer in the research division of Technicolor (multinational specialized in digital video and image technologies). My thesis was part of a project that aimed to analyze online movie-related forums.

Teaching experience

Academic supervision.....

Master's Thesis co-Supervisor

2015

Université de Lyon 2 - Technicolor

Lyon

Master in Data Mining and Knowledge Management.

Co-supervised the Master's Thesis of Zara Alaverdyan at Technicolor, entitled "Language-based

analysis in online forums" (supervisor : Julien Velcin).

Teaching

Vacataire March-April-May 2016

Université Paul Sabatier

Toulouse

Systèmes d'information et applications Web (TP, 24h)

Web applications with PHP and MySQL.

Vacataire March-April-May 2016

IUT Rangueil

Toulouse

UML design with Modelio (TP, 18h)

Teacher 2000

Epsilon Formación, http://www.epsilon-formacion.com/ Barcelona Elaboration and teaching of courses for first years students of Telecommunication Engineering (TD, 40h)

Master's Thesis (2010-2012)

title: Towards Trust-Aware Recommender Systems

supervisor: Ricard Gavaldà

PhD Thesis (2013-2016)

title: Automatic Role Detection in Online Forums.

supervisors: Bertrand Jouve (CNRS, U. Toulouse 2. Previously : U. Lyon 2), Julien Velcin (Université Lyon 2, ERIC Lab), Marie Guégan (Technicolor)

Languages

French: fluent Spanish: Native English: fluent (TOEFL iBT : 104) Catalan: Native

Publications

— Books : 1

International workshops : 2National conferences : 1

Patents: 1Journals: 1

Journals.

Lumbreras A., Velcin J., Guégan M., and Jouve B. Non-parametric clustering over user features and latent behavioral functions with dual-view mixture models. *Computational Statistics*, 2016.

Books.....

Toret J. (coord), Aguilera M., Aragón P., Calleja A. Lumbreras A., and Marín Ó. *Tecnopolítica y 15M : la potencia de las multitudes conectadas. Un estudio sobre la gestación y explosión del 15M.* Sociedad Red. Universitat Oberta de Catalunya Ed., 2015. Preprint edition :

http://tecnopolitica.net/sites/default/files/1878-5799-3-PB%20%282%29.pdf.

Conferences and Workshops (international).....

Lumbreras A., Lanagan J., Jouve B., and Velcin J. An insight into the analysis of roles in imdb. In *Complexity in social systems : from data to models*, 2013.

http://complexity-in-social-systems.u-cergy.fr/?page_id=18 (Cergy).

Lumbreras A. and Gavaldà R. Applying trust metrics based on user interactions to recommendation in social networks. In *International Conference on Advances in Social Networks Analysis and Mining - ASONAM*, pages 1191–1196, 2012. [First International Workshop on Social Knowledge Discovery and Utilization (SKDU 2012)] http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2456888.

Conferences and Workshops (national).....

Lumbreras A., Lanagan J., Velcin J., and Jouve B. Analyse des rôles dans les communautés virtuelles : définitions et premières expérimentations sur IMDb. In *Modèles et Analyses Réseau : Approches Mathématiques et Informatiques (MARAMI)*, pages 1–12, 2013.

http://lipn.univ-paris13.fr/marami2013/MARAMI13/Programme_2.html.

Seminars and Posters

Lumbreras A. Dynamiques dans les forums de discussions online. In *Modélisation des Réseaux en Histoire (MOREHIST*), 2015. http://preview.tinyurl.com/morehist [Workshop, Université Toulouse 2].

Lumbreras A. Methods and systems for clustering-based recommendations.

https://recerca.upc.edu/larca/en/news/seminar-by-alberto-lumbreras, 2015.

[Seminar at LARCA Lab, Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya, Barcelona].

Lumbreras A. Roles and dynamics of online conversations. https:

//www.irit.fr/-Seminaires-IRIT-UPS,902-?evtid=238&evttype=seminaire&lang=fr, 2015. [Seminar at IRIT, Toulouse].

Lumbreras A. Dynamique des discussions dans les forums. https://iscpif.fr/event/journee-interdisciplinaire-modelisation-des-interactions-temporelles/, 2016. [Seminar at Institut des Systèmes Complexes de Paris].

Lumbreras A. An introduction to markov chain monte carlo.

https://github.com/alumbreras/MCMC_intro, 2016. [Seminar at Technicolor, Rennes].

Lumbreras A., Guégan M., Julien J., and Jouve B. Clustering users features and latent behavioral functions. In *StatLearn*, 2015. http://statlearn.sfds.asso.fr/statlearn15/ [Poster, Grenoble].

Toret J., Aguilera M., Lumbreras A. Aragón P., Linares J., and Marín Ó. Gestation of the 15m, devices and augmented events, network system, emergence and self-organization. evolution of the network system. In *Digital culture, networks and distributed politics in the age of the Internet. From the Global Spring to the Net Democracy. Communication and Civil Society programme of the IN3 in Barcelona, Spain, in October 24-25*, 2012. http://ictlogy.net/review/?p=3992, Barcelona.

Publications submitted

Conferences and Workshops (international).....

Lumbreras A., Jouve B., Velcin J., and Guégan M. You are the way you structurally talk: Structural-temporal neighborhoods of posts to characterize users in online forums. In *International Conference on Advances in Social Networks Analysis and Mining - ASONAM*, 2016. [submitted].

Patents

Guégan M., Jouve B. Lumbreras A., and Velcin J. Methods and systems for clustering-based recommendations, July 2015. [EU Filled Patent, number 15306168.4].

Conferences and workshops organization

Dynamic Networks workshop

2016

(Institut de Systèmes Complexes de Toulouse)

Toulouse

http://isc-t.fr/language/fr/evenements/?event_id1=5

Hotel and trip reservation for invited speakers; communications (mailing, website announcements), agenda.

ECML-PKDD 2010

http://www.ecmlpkdd2010.org/index1f1e.html

Barcelona

Local logistics, reception and assistance for speakers during the conference.

References

References in academy.

— Bertrand Jouve (CNRS, U. Toulouse 2)

jouve@univ-tlse2.fr

— Julien Velcin (U. Lyon 2)

velcin@univ-lyon2.fr

Marie Guégan (Technicolor)

- marie.guegan@technicolor.com
- Ricard Gavaldà (U. Politècnica de Catalunya)

gavalda@cs.upc.edu

— Albert Bifet (Télécom ParisTech)

albert@albertbifet.com

References in industry (Telefónica R&D).....

— Enrique Garcia Illera (Direct Supervisor)

egi@tid.es

Carlos Domingo (Lab Director)

- https://about.me/carlosdomingo
- Xavier Amatriain (co-worker, Senior Researcher)
- http://xavier.amatriain.net/